conditions like osteoarthritis and even
general wear and tear are characterized
by damage to the cartilage in the knee,
the hip, and the spine. So, it stands to
reason that consuming collagen, a
structural protein that provides
strength and integrity to the joint,
could be consumed and help repair that
damage. But what does the research
actually say? Does the reasoning
actually stand up to the scientific
scrutiny? And are there potential
nuances that people are missing? Well,
for that I went through three studies to
try to understand how consuming collagen
affects our joints as a structural
protein in our cartilage. It is formed
into rod-like helical structures that
maintain the physical integrity around
the joint. Without it, we can get
instability in the joint or stiffness
due to a lack of elasticity and even
pain due to the inflammatory reaction in
the joint like that seen in some
arthritis. But the structural protein in
our cartilage is quite different from
the collagen that we typically consume.
Because collagen can be consumed
undenatured,
meaning its original structural form, or
it can be consumed in a denatured form,
meaning the helical structure of the
collagen has been unraveled. And in more
extreme cases like hydrayzeed collagen
peptides, it's also been cut up into
small fragments. Clearly only the first.
So the undenatured or native form is the
one similar to what we find in our
joints. Unfortunately, it's long been
believed that the pieces that make up
proteins like collagen called amino
acids are the only things that can
actually be absorbed. And they can only
be absorbed individually through these
amino acid transporters in the
intestinal cell membrane. However,
that's been debunked by research showing
that two and three amino acid peptides,
so two or three amino acids bonded
together, can also be absorbed as seen
here. We can see that the deptide
proline and glycine amino acids are
measured in the blood after absorption
indicating that the peptides can cross
the epithelial the intestinal barrier
through specific peptide transporters.
So now we have an opening for collagen
peptides. these smaller fragments to get
through and potentially be biologically
active. And we'll get to that in just a
minute. However, what about intact
collagen, the native collagen? Well, one
review mentions that native collagen can
also be absorbed. I have to admit, I was
pretty surprised by that announcement.
So, I did a bit of digging outside of
these main studies that I analyzed, and
guess what? There is some evidence that
might be true. Now, I'd like to take
some time to really dive deeper into the
literature before I'm convinced, but
this study did feed native collagen to
rats and then measured the impact their
blood had on joint cells. And they did
show an anti-inflammatory effect. So,
one explanation is that intact native
collagen cross the intestinal barrier
and cause this anti-inflammatory effect.
But until I actually see measures of
blood collagen, I remain skeptical.
Still, in this review, the researchers
point out that native collagen could
have an in between effect where a
section of the native collagen called an
epitope could create tolerance to
collagen. That's important for people
with autoimmune induced arthritis like
rheumatoid arthritis because the immune
system will invade into the joint
structure recognizing collagen's
proteins are other and destroying them.
However, if a person consumes collagen,
the immune system can sensitize
specialized cells that activate the
immune system to essentially get used to
collagen, thereby stopping this
overreaction by the immune system to
bodily collagen, stopping the
degradation of collagen. So, in short,
the consumed collagen is like a
distraction from your bodily structured
collagen. That's a pretty big deal
because you're shutting off the main
perpetrator that's causing all this
joint harm. And in said review, they
point out that the epitope, that section
of the native collagen, is enough. It's
not necessarily the full collagen
protein. The researchers argue that the
epitope can be absorbed by specialized
intestinal cells along with moving
between the cells. So in summary,
collagen epitopes get absorbed by
multiple mechanisms interacting with
specialized immune cells and these
immune cells then communicate to other
immune cells to change from a
pro-inflammatory state to an
anti-inflammatory state. There's a lot
more to say on this whole thing, but I
wouldn't say I'm entirely convinced yet
either. Anyway, while I think that the
potential anti-inflammatory mechanisms
of collagen consuming are well
fascinating, but what about the
non-inflammatory effects? Well, one of
the areas that has better research, at
least from an absorption perspective, is
collagen peptides. These proline
hydroxyproline glycine amino acids
bonded peptides have been shown to
interact with key collagen producing
cells called condondroytes. Exactly how
isn't exactly certain. possibly through
receptors on the cell surface. But we
know that these peptides are bioactive,
meaning it's not just giving the
substrate for native collagen
production, but actually changing the
signaling inside the cells to produce
more native collagen. Okay, again,
plenty more to say, but we have a few
mechanisms by which collagen, its native
form, its epitope, or the peptides
encourage joint collagen production and
reduce collagen degradation in the
joint. But we also know that we don't
base conclusions on mechanisms alone. So
are there human trials that indicate
benefit? No.
Of course there are, silly goose. See
here in this analysis, the researchers
pulled all the randomized control trials
that they could find on collagen
supplementation and joint function and
health. At the time of the analysis,
there were only five studies eligible.
But as I was working on this content, I
happened upon yet another analysis that
recently released and that one contained
11 studies. In both of these analyses by
separate research groups, they only
included studies comparing collagen
supplementation against placebo, so a
non-olagen inert substance. So when
opening the first analysis and we look
at a common joint health test called the
WMAC score, we see some noteworthy
results. The studies are on the left.
Then the numbers are the specifics of
each study. So the experiment up top
being collagen and the control being the
placebo condition. We aren't going to go
over all these numbers. Just pull your
eye to the right where we get a visual
representation of the results. The green
boxes are the results of the individual
studies. So the middle vertical line
indicates no benefit one way or another.
And if the studies lean to the right of
that line, there's a worse WMAC score,
meaning worse joint health with collagen
supplementation. And if they fall to the
left, that's an improvement in joint
health. That black diamond at the bottom
is the total effect. So all the studies
combined, clearly it falls to the left
of the line and definitely indicates a
lower WAC. So improved joint health. But
do we see that confirmed when we input
more studies? Well, lookie here, same
setup, but several more studies from the
updated analysis. Clearly, the results
remain. Even better, the effect size or
the overall amount of improvement was
about the same, too. So, two separate
analyses offering similar results
indicating collagen supplementation
works to improve joint health, even when
inputting more studies. Great. But there
are some things that you should know
before skipping off to start mass
consuming collagen. Before that, there's
work that's been done on collagen's
effects on pain and stiffness, different
amounts and timing of collagen, as well
as more that's been done on the
mechanisms of collagen interaction in
our body. That's all covered in the
extended version of the video that
you're currently watching, which is, as
you might already be tired of me
mentioning, included for the Physionic
Insiders. Membership also means that you
get access to the private podcast that
releases regularly along with live
sessions with me, a library of many,
many other videos, weekly articles with
actionable takeaways, and so much more.
Oh, and you also don't get advertised to
like I'm doing right now. So, you'll be
able to avoid all ads on everything,
which that alone may be worth it so that
I don't get on your nerves. But then
again, if I already get on your nerves,
more of me and the insiders isn't going
to help that. Anyway, the link to join
is in the description box. I would love
to have you join the community. Now,
there's several things that you should
know about collagen supplementation
studies, some good and some bad, mostly
bad. First, the effect size or the
improvement in the WMAC that we went
over was mild. A WAC score is between 0
and 96 with lower numbers being better.
Across both analyses, the reduction in
WAC was between 6 and 8 points. So, a
little less than a 10% improvement. Not
nothing, but not life-changing. Still,
even so, there's two more things to
consider in relation to that point. One,
while studies included were generally at
least 2 months long, that may simply be
the detected effect at that point in
time. Maybe four or six or 12 months,
you'd see further improvement. The
longest study was a little less than a
year and did not show much effect
though. Another consideration is these
studies are focused on people with
osteoarthritis. So in an already
troubled population, would we expect
even milder effects in people without
osteoarthritis?
So I'd characterize that as bad news.
But there is some semi good news, too.
For example, these analyses largely do
not include exercise. And the
researchers of some of these studies
indicate that to really stimulate joint
benefit, exercise should be paired with
collagen. I will say I opened up both
studies where exercise was included and
either the study was of a weak design or
the effect from collagen was negligible.
So while it's still a possibility, the
small amount of evidence that we have
right now is not impressive. One
additional critique is that no studies
compare against just plain protein. So,
we also don't know if there's just a
benefit of amino acids for collagen
independent of the collagen structure
itself. So, where does that leave us? To
collagen or not to collagen? A few
things to sum up. One, there's
definitely evidence that collagen mildly
improves joint health. Two, I would
stick to collagen peptides, so
hydrayzeed collagen, until more evidence
comes out on other forms. Three, there
are still holes in the collagen
literature that we need to fill in. So,
there's more research needed, especially
since all the collagen joint research in
is industry associated. So, overall,
consider collagen if you have osteo or
rheumatoid arthritis. But I don't expect
any miracles. And if you don't have
arthritis, we just don't have enough
good data to say. But one supplement
that has better evidence in its favor in
combating arthritis is the one that I
discuss right here. Or if you're
interested in more on collagen's
benefits, check out this right here.
I'll catch you over